I think we will get started.
So we're going to head back into public submissions on the
Conservation Amendment Bill, and our first
submitter today is Education Outdoors New Zealand,
who are joining us online. Welcome, Fiona. We can see you there.
You've got 15 minutes with us this morning, so we'll take your submission as
read, but we'll hand over to you for some opening remarks, and then open up for
questions. So over to you.
Tena koutou katoa. Thanks for the opportunity to speak to you today.
I'm Fiona MacDonald, tukangunga, ngā otutao yā hau.
I'm the Chief Executive for Education Outdoors New Zealand, or EONS.
EONS supports schools, careers, teachers, and outdoor
providers deliver safe, high-quality outdoor education and
education outside the classroom across Aotearoa New Zealand.
We're here today because public conservation land is one of the most important
classrooms in the country.
Mm.
It's where young people learn to read the weather, the rivers.
It's where they learn to walk with others, make decisions,
manage uncertainty, listen to local stories, and understand
ecosystem systems, and experience their own
capabilities. It's where many ākonga
will sleep in a tent for the first time, cross a river, hear native
birds in their habitat, see stars away from city lights, and
understand that conservation and restoration is not an abstract idea.
It's something they can participate in.
And that's why EONS' message today, reinforcing our
submission, is really simple. The Conservation Act must place
conservation first. Education, recreation, and
public access and enjoyment clearly sit in behind that and should
always be consistent with conservation.
And commercial activity should only occur where it supports and does not
limit, undermine, or displace those first two purposes.
We're not opposed to commercial activity.
Well-managed tourism and appropriate concessions can definitely help people
access and appreciate special places.
But the Act must be very clear about the order of priorities.
Public conservation land shouldn't be treated primarily as an
economic development platform. If conservation is weakened,
then everything that's built on it is weakened, too; outdoor education,
recreation, cultural connection, community wellbeing, and the
visitor economy.
People don't come to Aotearoa New Zealand to see dammed rivers,
industrialized wild places, demodiversity ones, come for the
mountains, the amazing views, wildlife, culture and
adventure, story, and the experience of being in places that feel
alive. The economic benefit that comes from tourism depends
on health and integrity of nature.
For schools, the environment matters in very practical ways.
A teacher taking a group into a conservation area is not just
taking students for a walk. They may be there to teach outdoor
education through decision-making, risk awareness, leadership,
and care for place. They might be teaching science through direct
observation of ecosystems, PE through movement and challenge, or
geography
through landforms and human impact.
They may be supporting te reo Maori, mātauranga Māori through place names,
pūrākau, whakapapa, and relationships with whenua and
wai.
Teaching citizenship by helping young people understand public good,
shared responsibility, and the long-term consequences of the decisions we
make about places.
That learning can't be replicated fully in a classroom, on a screen, or
through a worksheet. People learn differently when they're
in place. They notice things. They ask different questions.
They understand scale, interdependence, and consequence in a
way that's impossible to recreate indoors.
Healthy, flourishing environments support healthy, flourishing
people. And the opposite is true when
young people grow up with reduced access to healthy
places. We lose an education pathway
into environmental understanding, resilience, cultural connection,
confidence, and care.
And that's why EONS is asking the committee to apply an intergenerational
test to this act.
The question should not be what economic use can we enable now?
The question should be, what will future generations inherit because
of the decisions we make today?
Will they inherit a healthier ecosystem?
Will they inherit access? Will they inherit places where they can still learn,
explore, listen, observe, challenge themselves, and develop
a lifelong ethic of care?
Will mana whenua relationships with place be upheld and strengthened?
Will both mātauranga Māori and ecological science inform decisions?
And will public conservation land still feel like public conservation
land?
If the answer's uncertain, the Act should take a proactive path.
And protect conservation values.
We do recognise that the system needs to be modernised.
Processes can be slow, complex, and frustrating.
So we support any reform that improves clarity,
efficiency, consistency and good decision-making, but it must
improve how the conservation system works, not change why it
exists.
And our concern is with wording such as "recognise economic
opportunities" and "enable the use and development to the greatest
possible extent."
That's creating the wrong pull on the system.
It risks asking DOC decision-makers to look for development
pathways rather than first asking what the place needs in
order to remain healthy or to be restored to health, be
resilient in the future, and be available for public good for future
generations.
Conservation land's not empty land waiting for higher economic use.
It already has immense value.
It holds biodiversity, whakapapa, history, identity,
quiet and dark skies, wildlife, mahinga kai,
stories and memories. And lots of those are values that can't be rebuilt
once they're lost. They can't be offset or have a price put on them.
And therefore, we really believe that the Act needs to make the
hierarchy unmistakable. Protect and enhance natural,
cultural, and historic values first.
Secondly, support education, public access, responsible
recreation, and public enjoyment where they're consistent with
conservation. And thirdly, allow tourism, commercial
activity, and economic uses only where they
are demonstratively consistent with conservation and do not
materially compromise the above values.
The hierarchy is not anti-tourism.
It's the foundation for long-term tourism.
EONZ also asks the committee to give stronger attention to education as
a public good outcome for conservation land.
Outdoor education is one of the ways that young people become future
conservation advocates.
When a student's helped planting with track care
biosecurity or low-impact travel, they're not just
visiting, they're learning stewardship and tiakitanga.
They're learning that the outdoors is not simply a place to consume, but a
place to understand, respect, care for, and return to.
And these young people, they're going to be our future teachers, parents,
guides, conservation volunteers, decision-makers,
community, and mana whenua leaders.
If we want a society that supports conservation, young people need
meaningful opportunities to experience conservation land.
So we'd like to see the removal of unnecessary barriers for
not-for-profit outdoor education.
Schools can undertake outdoor education on public conservation land,
rightly exempt from concessions.
But not-for-profit outdoor education providers delivering similar education
experiences, often in partnership with schools, are still required to hold
concessions.
The learning's similar, the students are similar, the places are similar, so it's
hard to justify the distinction.
And schools are increasingly reliant on support of these specialist outdoor
providers to deliver more complex outdoor education safely.
They're not commercial tourism operators seeking
private gain from conservation land.
They're often charitable trusts or tertiary education
organisations whose purpose is education, youth development, and
wellbeing. And when concession costs, uncertainty, delays,
or conditions on those programs make them less
viable, the result's not better conservation.
It's fewer young people learning in te taiao.
So we ask the committee to recommend adding outdoor education to the list of
activities that can be carried out on conservation land without a consent,
where that activity is delivered by a not-for-profit organisation.
We also would ask the committee to ensure Te Tiriti o
Waitangi is explicit in the Act and in the National
Conservation Statement. Mana whenua relationships with
place shouldn't be treated as a consultation step.
They must be part of decision-making from the beginning, and the National
Conservation Policy Statement should make
or should provide clear direction for mana whenua decision-making,
iwi and hapū relationships with place, tikanga-led approaches to access and
learning, and the use of mātauranga Māori alongside ecological
science. That's not separate from outdoor education, it's
central. When young people learn in places shaped by mana whenua
knowledge, histories, and tikanga, they're more likely to
develop respect, care, responsibility, and long-term commitment
to te taiao,
the environment.
And finally, we ask that access for students, schools, kura,
youth organisations, and not-for-profit
outdoor education providers is protected.
Access to te taiao,
the environment and conservation estate is an equity issue.
It's a wellbeing issue, and it's an education issue.
And conservation land should never become a
consumer experience available to only those who can afford it.
So in closing,
we ask the committee to amend the bill so that
conservation remains the primary purpose for the conservation system.
We ask that education is recognised as a core public
good outcome,
that commercial activity is clearly subordinate and is only
enabled when it generally supports conservation
outcomes,
that unnecessary barriers, such as requiring concessions for outdoor
education providers, are removed So there's
consistency between schools and not-for-profit after-education
providers. And we ask the committee to take the, a long view.
The future of conservation in Aotearoa, uh, will not be secured only
by rules, plans, and concessions.
It's also secured by young people who know and love these places,
understand their responsibilities, and can imagine themselves as
kaitiaki, educators, advocates, and careful users
of te— te taiao. Healthy places grow
healthy people. Healthy people are more likely to care for healthy
places, and the Conservation Act should protect that relationship
for all our mokopuna into the future.
Thank you
very much, Fiona. Um, we've just got time for a couple of questions.
We'll start with Celia.
Thank you very much. Thank you, Fiona.
You're welcome.
I'm just going to narrow down on the concession question,
and, um, the cost of concessions if you've
got an external provider. Do you think that that could, um,
impact the safety of children because schools and parents
choose the cheaper option rather than the safer option?
Yes, that's definitely one of our concerns, and also
it's often, uh, the, um, conditions that are
put around the concession, so they're only allowed to take a certain number
of students, which limits the viability of running that
program, and that's one of the concession requirements that
schools don't have to face.
Thank you.
So we want to reduce down those barriers so schools and students, uh, are
enabled to get out there in the safest possible way.
Thank you. Priyanka.
Kia ora.
Kia ora. Um, uh, thanks for your submission.
I just have a question around the point that you've made, um,
y-you've said that not all commercial activity is harmful, but the bill's
direction's too broad, and you've got a, um, a few
suggestions in the table around a, a hierarchy,
um, and, uh, the bit that I want to ask you about
is your point to remove or substan- substantially redraft
clauses that require economic opportunities to be recognized and
enabled to the greatest extent practicable.
Um, would removing the greatest extent practicable along
with the other amendments that you've suggested be enough, or were you
thinking of something else in terms of redrafting specific
clauses?
Um, I think that would certainly go a ways towards, um,
helping. What we're really concerned about is making sure
that the priority really stays in that conservation
space, and those are the key drivers around is
it, um, is this activity going to improve the health,
support restoration if that needs to happen?
Um, so anything that can shift and make sure the priority stays with
conservation, then with education, recreation, and public access,
and lastly, enabling commercial
activity, whether that's tourism or other activities.
Thank you.
Thank you. Look, we'll take one last question from Grant McCollum.
Yeah, thank you very much. We enjoyed your presentation.
Just quickly, so obviously, to enjoy the
outdoors, you need, you know, good tracks, well-maintained, all that sort of thing.
Um, and so you obviously recognize there is a place for
having, you know, to charge, uh, appropriately for, for example, the foreign
visitors, the levy we're talking about here in this case, but, and to help, to help
maintain those sorts of things and to maintain economic activity where
appropriate-
Yes
... un-underneath the conservation banner. Is that, you're okay with that?
Yes. Yes, we recognize that we need to pay for having high
quality, keeping tracks safe, and enabling as
much access as we can within that conservation
framework.
Thank you very much.
Yes.
Thank you very much, Fiona, for your submission and, of course, for all the
work that you're doing in terms of educating our younger ones coming through.
Yes.
We can all relate to our first time out in the wilderness in tents and things,
so thank you very much. Um, appreciate it.
Ka kite.
So our next submission this morning, um, we have Te
Runanga o Ngāi Tahu
are here with us in person. Welcome.
Thank you.
Welcome to the select committee this morning.
You have 15 minutes with us, so we'll hand over to you to open up-
Kia ora
... and then we'll open for questions.
Thank you. Tena koutou katoa. Ngā mihi nui kia koutou.
Uh, thank you, Madam Chair, uh, and members of the committee for the opportunity to
appear today. I'm appearing as Chief Executive Officer of Te Runanga o Ngāi Tahu,
and um, alongside me is the ōtāka pukeko Edward Allison.
Uh, this bill, uh, not only fails to deliver the new age of cooperation
that has been promised to Ngāi Tahu by the Crown,
but it also puts our settlement at risk.
We only have 15 minutes today, and as such, I strongly encourage anyone
reading this transcript or listening to these proceedings, uh, to read our
submission in full, uh, where our concerns are outlined in detail.
Uh, as set out in our written submission, Ngāi Tahu has long advocated
for transformative conservation reform that is modern,
supports a thriving te ao Tūroa, and upholds the promises of
Te Tiriti o Waitangi.
The current Conservation Amendment Bill does not meet those goals,
and that is why Ngāi Tahu opposes the bill.
I'll now invite Edward Allison, one of the negotiators of the Ngāi Tahu settlement,
to begin.
Uh, tena koe to you, Madam Chair, members of the committee.
Ko Edward Allison toku iko.
Uh, why conservation matters to Ngāi Tahu in, in the, in the co-
settlement context. For Ngāi Tahu, conservation
cannot be separated from mahinga kai.
Mahinga kai is not simply about gathering food, it reflects our
identity as a people
It is how our tipuna lived, traveled, traded, exercised their
rangatiratanga, and related to taiao.
These are not simply public conservation lands we are talking about
today, or simply administrative reforms.
For us, this is about the places our tipuna occupied,
named, cared for, and gathered from over countless
generations. When considering this bill, we
ask the committee
to remember that it is making decisions that affect how the Crown
recognizes and actively protects these long-standing
relationships, and how it supports Ngāi Tahu
rangatiratanga
in our takiwā, a commitment the Crown confirmed in our Ngāi
Tahu settlement.
In terms of the redress, the journey to settlement was long,
and in the early 1980s, Ngāi Tahu brought together
what we call the nine tall trees.
Eight of those were related to the major
settlements, land sales in Te Waipounamu.
The ninth was related to mahinga kai.
That reflected the importance Ngāi Tahu
placed on regaining access,
influence, and the relationship we have with our
natural environment.
So by the time the negotiations occurred, much of the land within
our takiwā had been passed through to the conservation
estate, and in practical terms, large areas of
that land were not available for return through settlement
negotiations.
And as our written response states, that had a profound
influence on the nature of our settlement and what that looked like.
We did not seek ownership of the entire
conservation estate, and instead, we negotiated
mechanisms that would recognize our status as tangata whenua,
and maintain our relationship and management of those
places. These arrangements included taupuni,
deeds of recognition, taonga species recognition,
and representation on conservation boards in the New Zealand
Conservation Authority, among others.
They were not incidental, those mechanisms.
They were ways in which Ngāi Tahu relationship with the conservation
estate was recognized where ownership could not
be returned.
And central to those arrangements was our understanding
of Section 4 of the Conservation Act.
We understood that future conservation management decision-making would
continue to be guided by a statutory
obligation to give effect to the principles of the Treaty of
Waitangi.
That formed part of the foundation upon which the Crown and Ngāi Tahu
rebuilt their relationship in the conservation space, and
we have continued to do so to this day.
We are therefore very concerned whenever there
may be an attempt
to prescribe or narrow what Section 4
requires, and which we consider Section 4A,
as proposed, may do.
That will risk over time, that's the meaning of the
Section 4,
to be reduced from what it is, a powerful treaty obligation,
into a procedural checklist of when iwi are to be
consulted, and the time frames for that to
occur. So the proposed new Section 4A does
not uphold those foundations of our
settlement in how the Crown must actively protect iwi,
hapū rights and interests. For the avoidance of
doubt,
Section 4 of the proposed bill must be removed.
And I want to close by saying how
disappointing it is to be here 30 years after settlement,
talking about these things at this
point in time.
Commitments that were made through the settlement to
Ngāi Tahu,
30 years on. So Paul will now pass back to
you.
The key question from Ngāi Tahu is not whether conservation reform
should occur, it is when and how.
Our settlement and our many discussions with the Crown since then
have spoken of a new age of cooperation.
It is something that we take very seriously, yet we've never seen that
realized.
As Edward has explained,
conservation redress is a key part of the Ngāi Tahu settlement.
These are solemn commitments between Ngāi Tahu and the Crown.
For me, the key points this committee must consider, and
which are set out in our submission are:
arrangements proposed through full and final settlement
are being removed without replacement.
A commitment is being made to uphold settlements and
honor te Tiriti, while at the same time weakening the treaty
clause.
Ngāi Tahu representation that has been in place since settlement
is being removed, despite local communities acknowledging its
value.
Decision-making is being shifted away from local communities and
into centralized ministerial processes.
Collectively, these changes put our settlement at risk,
put the DOC estate at risk, and diminish local and
iwi voices.
This is not good enough,
and it is why Ngāi Tahu opposes the bill.
I do not want to take up all of our time, as we're keen to answer questions, but I
will finish by reiterating this.
Ngāi Tahu remains committed to the new age of cooperation that has been
promised. We are ready for genuine discussions
about what a new era of conservation could look like
However, we are still waiting for the Crown to step up and join us at the table.
Kia ora koutou, we're happy to take your questions.
Thank you very much for that thorough submission.
We've got time for some questions. We'll go to Lann Farm first.
Moriina koutou. Thank you so much for your submission and for being here in person.
Thank you for such a clear submission.
I wanted to ask about your fourth
position in your written submission,
because it is about a streamlined planning
and concessions regime, and you're saying that
as much as this bill is saying that it's going to make things better, you're
interpreting it as creating unnecessary
complexity, and you kind of step through the levels of
National Conservation Policy Statement area plans,
past concessions, and then visitor amenity areas.
Can you help the committee understand
what is it within there that
you think could actually be improved?
And I'm noting it is a big area. So just what would be
the biggest things that you think we could change, or
change in these bills to help that whole situation?
Well, I think there is room for improvement in terms of reducing one layer of the
plans, perhaps.
Mm-hmm.
Which would bring some efficiency,
simplification to that. The
difficulty with the proposals is that the decision
making, public voice, and certainly tangata whenua voice
is taken away and it is centralized.
So the decision making is centralized and takes it away from the
local community, local interests.
So that is a difficulty, one of the difficulties we have
with it.
Mm-hmm.
Brown.
Yeah, I'm just curious. So obviously this bill has
been taking a while in the making. It hasn't just turned up.
What level of consultation and engagement have you had through this
process?
We engaged a huge amount with the department on a regular
basis,
and
our kaiwhakahaere with the minister.
Mm-hmm.
I think part of this, though, is when I saw
that two-year window that we're going to have to sort of renegotiate our treaty
settlements, I was questioning whether that was actually real.
You're asking us all to renegotiate our settlements over a two-year period.
So it just feels like it's just being rammed through.
It's just a-- I can't see how that's quality lawmaking to do that in
such a compressed timeframe. So engagement, it
happens regularly, but we still want to take the time, as Edward has said,
the journey that we went on over those generations.
Mm-hmm.
We want to take the time to get this right for our mokopuna.
Mm-hmm. Just kind of a bit of a supplementary on that.
You do talk about support in principle economic use,
but only where it supports, not displaces the long-term health and integrity of-
Absolutely. Look-
And so because obviously, it also must present a lot of opportunity
for Ngāi Tahu as well, to be able to
do more on the land as well.
Absolutely. For us, it's not a question of preservation and locking things
up. We utilize the environment. We understand that, and we have absolute
economic interest and interest in ensuring infrastructure's
improved and all those elements. But it's got to be done the right way, and it's
got to be done with us. As I said, new age of cooperation, that is the
commitment. We want to be part of those conversations.
Not just conversations, but part of that right the way through that process.
So we understand there is a significant deficit in investment in the conservation
estate. We understand the challenges in biodiversity.
We understand all those things you're talking about, but we want to make sure this
is done in the right way.
Okay. Lann.
Bianca, actually. Sorry, I didn't see you there on the Zoom.
We'll go to-
Thank you.
I have a bit of a sup to that line of questioning around the
engagement.
You'd mentioned that it's not just about engagement, you
want to be part of the process. Keen to better understand what
that would've looked like.
And my main question is, you ended your
oral presentation by saying that you don't support the bill.
Keen to get a sense of whether you think, if the changes are made as you've laid
out in your written submission as well, whether this is a
bill that can be improved or whether you think it needs to be
dispensed with and started again.
The journey we've been on has been long.
When we settled, that did not magically then make that
treaty compliant. It's taken us 30 years nearly, and we're building
going forward. This has been a huge effort both on
ourselves and for the department as well going
forward. There are fundamental aspects in the bill that just
will not simply work. 4A is going to undermine that
very treaty relationship and
really just be a transactional relationship.
Giving effect to the principles of the Treaty of Waitangi takes
effort, concentrated thinking, and
genuine relationships. So number one, that is a
huge issue with this proposed bill, is the
modernization,
is the Section 4, 4A. And
while there has been engagement, as I say,
30 years of building on our settlement requires quite a lot of time
to then engage and understand from the
minister and the proposed changes, how they will work and
how they will best reflect
Those things that we settled in the Crown confirmed back in
1998. So
some fundamental issues there with the proposed bill.
The centralization of decision making will be critical.
Our hapū, our iwi, at place,
the ability to
be sure that we'll have the appropriate level of engagement
is critical. And I think my reading of Section
4A will considerably diminish that.
Thank you. Look, just one last question from Lam.
Kia ora.
You made it really clear about the hard won seats on the New
Zealand Conservation Authority and also the conservation boards.
And I'm also aware, I can't remember the terminology, but you've sort of got
species representatives with Te Runanga.
Can you help the committee understand what does that look like for
Te Runanga, and what do the species representatives do?
The taonga species, there's a considerable schedule of them.
And so there's species recovery processes.
We have representation, engagement with DOC on
those. On the conservation boards, we have dedicated
seats, as well as having a dedicated seat on the Conservation
Authority. That has been huge in terms of bringing Ngāi Tahu
into the picture, being actively engaged, sitting there with
public interest, because that's the public voice, very important in this
process, and also, of course, engaging with
director general,
minister in all aspects of conservation.
They have been huge innovations going forward.
Prior to settlement, we were not seen as a party, or
we didn't seem to have a place. Was directly involved in developing those
mechanisms because I was also on those roles, and it
was a very contested place. So they've been huge
in terms of building partnership, not only with DOC, but with all
public participants in the conservation
place. The taupēne, very important, placing their values
on special places,
and
quite a number of other mechanisms. There's a huge number of mechanisms.
They are tools that bring us in, enable us to
participate, exercise our rakitira taku in working
partnership.
Kia ora. Thank you.
Look, thank you very much. We will have to end it there. We've met time.
We do appreciate your time today and obviously coming up in person.
Really valuable discussion. So thanks for the submission. Thank you.
Kia ora. Thank you.
Thank you.
Thank you very much.
Yeah. Thank you.
So we now move to our next submitter, World
Wide Fund for Nature New Zealand.
Who are also joining us in person today.
Welcome to the committee this morning.
So you have 15 minutes with us, so take your submission as read, and we'll hand
over to you for your opening introductions. Thank you.
Thanks. Thank you.
Tēnā koutou katoa. My name's Kaitlin Owens. This is Jamie Fowler.
Thank you for the opportunity to speak to you today about the Conservation
Amendment Bill. We want to start by saying that WWF does not
support the bill in its current form.
Public conservation land and waters belong to the people of Aotearoa New Zealand.
They protect some of our most important and irreplaceable natural places.
They provide a home for threatened species and help sustain the natural environment
that underpins so much of our economy.
And let's face it, they're also what draw people in from all around the world.
But these places are about more than that.
Our connection to nature is part of what it means to be a New Zealander.
These places are the forests, rivers, wetlands, coastlines, and mountains where
people go tramping, swimming, camping, and fishing.
And as we've already seen from the incredible public response to this bill, these
are the places that Kiwis want to protect and be able to pass on to our children
and grandchildren.
And in the midst of a biodiversity crisis, when we have one of the highest rates of
species extinction in the world, around 4,000 species at risk of extinction,
these places have never been more important.
The biggest problem facing New Zealand's conservation system is not that it's too
difficult to develop conservation land.
It is that we are losing nature at an alarming rate.
For WWF, that has to be the starting point for reform.
The question we should be asking is how will these changes strengthen and
improve our ability to protect and restore nature?
And that's where our fundamental concern with this bill lies.
Look, we do recognize there are genuine problems with the way our conservation
system currently operates, and we do support the need to modernize the system.
There are longstanding inefficiencies in concession processes and
conservation management planning that have been a source of frustration for DOC and
those who engage with it.
And we do think there's a legitimate case for reducing unnecessary administrative
burden, and that there are some sensible proposals in this bill to do that.
But for us, this bill goes much further than modernizing
processes. It fundamentally changes New Zealand's conservation system in
ways that risk weakening longstanding protections for nature.
This bill elevates economic development within conservation decision-making,
increases opportunities for development on conservation land, weakens public
participation, and reduces independent oversight.
Ultimately, we recommend that the bill be withdrawn and substantially rewritten to
ensure that conservation remains the overriding purpose of our conservation system.
Our first and biggest concern is the proposed change to the purpose and
direction of conservation management.
The bill introduces a new function for the Department of Conservation, requiring it
to recognize economic opportunities arising from conservation land and to
enable that use and development to the greatest extent practicable.
We don't think that's a minor administrative change.
It represents a significant shift from a conservation first framework towards one
where economic development is elevated and becomes an explicit objective of the
conservation system.
Economic activity can already occur on conservation land through established
concession processes where it's consistent with conservation objectives.
So the question is, why does economic use and development need to be elevated
into an explicit function of DOC? We're concerned that doing so
changes the fundamental balance of the system and risks moving us away
from the system towards one where economic development becomes an objective in its
own right. We're also really concerned that this provision was added in at a late
stage and was not included in the proposals consulted on in February 2025.
Mm.
A change with such significant implications for the department's core functions
should have been subject to proper public scrutiny.
In our view, this late stage change needs to be removed in its entirety.
I'm now going to hand over to Jamie to talk through some of our concerns.
Great. So our second concern is the way the bill creates a more
development-focused framework while removing important environmental
safeguards. So the proposed pre-approved and exempt activity
provisions would reduce scrutiny for certain activities.
And so we understand the rationale for when you've got low risk activities,
to be able to
approve those more quickly. But we're concerned that the activities that have
greater environmental impacts could also proceed without
more robust case-by-case assessment.
So particularly important here is the cumulative effect of multiple
developments within these kind of areas.
An individual activity might appear relatively minor, but obviously, when you
multiply activities that take place over time, there are lots
of combined effects on ecosystems, species, and habitats that can be quite
significant. So this is particularly concerning when nature is already
under immense pressure.
The provisions relating to the visitor amenity areas, in particular,
also create risks of ecosystem disturbance, habitat degradation, and
increased pressure on already vulnerable environments.
Again, it's the cumulative effect here that really concerns us.
We're not arguing that every activity should be unnecessarily
bureaucratic. We are arguing that efficiency cannot come at the
expense of environmental bottom lines.
So we recommend strengthening these provisions so that conservation values
are maintained or enhanced and that independent ecological assessment
is required where appropriate.
We should also note that we welcome the government's stated intention to remove
the provisions relating to the exchange and disposal of conservation land following
the outpouring of public concern.
Our public conservation land shouldn't be treated as a collection of bits and bobs
that can simply be traded away. Kiwis have certainly made that known.
So given this issue has been well traversed, we obviously won't go into further
detail on it today, other than to say we strongly support that change and encourage
the committee to ensure these provisions are removed from the bill.
Our final concern is the weakening of public oversight and treaty obligations.
The bill significantly increases the ministerial decision-making powers
while reducing the role of the New Zealand Conservation Authority and conservation
boards. These bodies provide important independent oversight and ecological
expertise and community perspectives.
Reducing them to largely advisory functions weakens the
checks and balances and increases the risk that decisions become influenced by the
short-term political considerations rather than long-term environmental
stewardship.
Public conservation land and waters are a shared national treasure, and their
management should reflect the values and interests of those communities they
belong to. Instead, the proposed changes would narrow the circumstances
in which concession applications must be publicly notified, meaning
many applications could proceed without public awareness or scrutiny.
Public participation is further constrained by removing any automatic
right for submitters to be heard. Hearings provide an important opportunity,
obviously, to test evidence and ensure decision-makers hear directly from affected
communities and stakeholders.
We're also concerned that some of the provisions around treaty obligations and
Māori engagement risk reducing what is currently the
strongest obligation to give effect to treaty principles into something more like
a procedural checklist.
You would have heard this obviously from Matua Edward Ellison in the previous
submission. Mātauranga Māori and Māori stewardship approaches provide
critical insights into long-term ecosystem health and biodiversity
protection. At its core, effective conservation
depends on ensuring enduring partnerships and
shared stewardship. Meaningful engagement with treaty partners is not
simply a procedural requirement, it is fundamental to
achieving conservation outcomes,
and that these outcomes are durable and they're equitable, and they're
reflective of Aotearoa's unique context.
We therefore recommend restoring stronger notification and hearing
rights, strengthening the roles of conservation boards and
NZCA, and ensuring early, meaningful, and properly resourced iwi and
hapū engagement with greater opportunities for Māori leadership in
conservation decision-making.
Ultimately, we think the conservation system works best when decisions are informed
by strong science, independent oversight, public participation, and
genuine partnership with Tangata Whenua.
To conclude, WWF agrees that Aotearoa, New Zealand's conservation system needs
modernization. We support better processes, greater efficiency,
and removing unnecessary barriers to effective conservation management.
But this bill goes much further than that.
So it changes the direction of our conservation system in ways that
risk weakening protections for nature.
As Caitlin mentioned, at a time when we're facing a biodiversity crisis, we need
reforms that actually strengthen our ability to protect and restore nature, not
make it easier to develop the places we're already struggling to protect.
Reform of this magnitude must be grounded in a clear and unwavering commitment
to protect our biodiversity, maintaining ecological integrity, and upholding
the public interest. The decisions here will determine what is left for the next
generation. The rivers, the forests, the wetlands, the
coastlines, and mountains we protect today are the places future generations
should still be able to know and explore and love.
WWF urges the committee to withdraw and substantially rewrite this bill, so that
instead of weakening our conservation framework, it creates the strong,
modern system Aotearoa needs to halt and reverse biodiversity loss and
restore our natural environment.
Thank you for your time today, and we welcome any questions.
Thank you very much for your submission. Look, we'll go first to Grant McCallum.
Yeah. Morning, great to see you both.
I want to touch on the
whole land sale and disposal discussion that created a lot of
angst, you might say. Do you
feel there's any place at all for the DOC to be able to
sell and/or swap land?
Of course. There's already provisions that do that.
Mm-hmm.
And I understand that the minister feels that those aren't
adequate-
Mm-hmm
... or he doesn't want to resource them, I'm not sure.
But, it's different to say
we're going to kind of blanket, and I understand the minister, that wasn't his
intention, but that was the way it was kind of drafted, is to do the-
Absolutely
... kind of blanket land and exchange disposal.
So you could do a schedule in the legislation that
specifically references the places that you're actually looking at.
You could do a prioritized list of those areas.
Well, there's-
There's other options there.
Yeah. Well, it's interesting you say all that.
I think that would be really some project to identify
all the land bits and pieces of... Because I suppose my concern is just
the process of doing it at the moment's very clunky and very difficult, from what I
understand.
And I'll give you a classic example.
For me, it makes a lot more sense for DOC, in my little
place in North Whangara,
we had a weather event.
The local hall, big slip came down behind it.
Turns out that's on DOC land, so DOC are going to have to fix the
slip. That's going to be money that could be spent on looking after the
biodiversity challenges that you talk about. So that's the sorts of things.
Would you think it's a good idea to actually design a system that makes it easier
to actually, where appropriate, to dispose of land, rather than, because it seems
very clunky at the moment.
Sure. I think you need to consider things like
scale and there's a lot of considerations, so I think the main concern is
around just having a blanket provision that-
Sure
... allows you to do that. But I think if you have some specific
considerations in place that kind of allow for a more robust
analysis of whether or not that area is actually suitable, I think that
could work.
Okay. Thank you. Appreciate it.
Thank you. Lam.
Yeah. Thank you so much for your submission this morning.
You touched on, in your submission,
how much
improvement, shall we say, conservation legislation needs.
Where would you direct efforts? This is
one bill, but you've noted a few in your submission that
you think working on those, potentially
in
concert with this one,
could
get us to a more significant and enduring transformative space for
conservation. Do you want to touch on those for the committee?
Sure.
Yeah, look, I think many of you are probably familiar with the fact that
we've got quite antiquated conservation legislation across the board, whether
you're talking about the Marine Reserves Act from 1971, you're talking about the
Wildlife Act, it was-
1950s
... 1950s.
Yeah. It shows.
Yeah. I think you could pick any of them really, and
start to prioritize, I guess, a
package.
Mm-hmm.
So efficiency, yes, but there's a package here-
Mm
... and I think it's really important to make sure that we're not losing sight of
the core function of DOC, and making sure that we're prioritizing some
of that as well.
Mm. Thank you.
Brilliant. Well, thank you very much for your submission today.
We appreciate your time and coming in in person.
So, yeah, some good points raised there, so thank you.
Thanks a lot.
Thanks. Thank you here very
much.
Thank you.
So, we will go back into private session now.
That brings us to the end of our public submissions this morning